How good!  Thank you very much.
My name is Xavier Guix.
I am a psychologist, a writer,
I have written a few books.  I will
only mention two,
the first and the last.
The first one, which, by
the way, has just been updated,
is titledNeither I explain myself, nor I understand.
It is a treatise
on human communication.
And the last book is titled
The Problem of Being Too Good.
When I started in this world...
Not in the world of psychology,
but the other world.
I was an actor.
I dedicated myself to the world of show business.  I
was an artist
and, in addition, a
radio and television presenter...
In other words,
my life was directed towards the
field of communication
and entertainment.
A bohemian life, they said at my house.
This happened in the years..., he
must have been 18,
until 28 or 30, and possibly,
when
the Barcelona Olympics took place.
And after the Olympics, in 1993, there was
an economic recession,
maybe the older ones can remember it,
and this economic recession
hit me hard.  It
occurred to me that this happens
to so many people when they go through a crisis,
that they are left with one hand in front
and the other behind,
and I had to do what you have
probably read
and heard many times,
reinvent your life.
Then, I had to reinvent it.
What I learned at that moment
was that I thought I
had my life figured out.
How many times do we think
that our life is already resolved?
Somehow, the fact of having
a more or less permanent job,
the fact of having a
more or less stable life,
the fact of having a life
with a certain comfort,
the fact that you do more or less the
same things every day,
the fact that you
are with the same people every day,
makes you believe
that your life is already resolved.
Happily resolved
and, instead,
your life changes in an instant.
So,
the first thing I learned was this.
Don't get too carried away
or lead your life
thinking that things are already done,
that you have them resolved,
because, as Mercedes Sosa sang,
life changes, everything changes.  And it
changes in an instant.
The second thing I learned,
oddly enough, was something unexpected.
I thought that, a little bit to foresee
what I could do in my life...
Because it's the first thing you ask yourself:
"And now, what?
What will I do?".
Well, it occurred to me,
instead of looking to the future, to
go back to the past.
I made an act of nostalgia,
but not painful nostalgia,
not nostalgia of this kind: "Oh,
how I miss those moments!",
but rather:
"What is it that I, as a child, as a young man, had
realized that I had a talent for,
that was useful for this,
that I really liked?".
So, I
often tell people
when they come to the clinic
and are lost, I
ask them this question:
"What did you like to do when you were young?
What were you good at?
What gave you happiness?"
Then,
I delved into this past
and found that, indeed,
around the age of 18, 17, 18,
I already had a huge inclination
towards psychology.
He was that person to whom friends go
and tell them about the things that are happening to them.
And I remember that,
at that moment, he showed
an enormous ability
to see the mechanisms
that were working in that person
so that they realized what
was happening to them.
So I learned another lesson.
No matter how much you tell
someone what to do, they
won't do it.
First, because you say so.
And second, because you also don't understand
the mechanisms that move
this person to do what they do.
But it doesn't matter, it didn't matter.  They
must suffer whatever they must suffer.
They have to go their own way.
And we
cannot stand in their way.
Then, sometimes, you get lost
because you want to follow
the same thing your peers do,
the same thing everyone else does.
Sometimes you go home to your family,
who tells you:
"No, stop being silly.
What's this show business? You'll
never make a living.
You have to be a civil servant,
that's what you have to be."
In my youth,
the two things
that all young people had to do
was work in an institution,
a bank or savings bank,
or as a civil servant.
This was our destiny.
And soon buy an apartment,
have a partner, get married,
have an apartment, start having children...
This was the destiny that awaited us.
And, instead...
I see you make faces like this...
I think you older people understand me,
that you've had to go through
a bit of this.
Well, then...
No, no.
We must return to life
what life has given us as a gift.
As if it were something for us,
for us to develop
and then deliver it to life
in the best way we know how.
And lastly, don't set limitations on yourself,
especially not because of age.
Age is not in the body.
Yes, the body has its reasons, of course,
but we live according to this and according to that.
Therefore, there is no age.
Don't limit yourself, please, do
n't think
that your life is over,
don't think that, well,
what are you going to do with your life,
don't think that you're already grown up.
Please
give yourself what you think
life is asking of you, calling you,
and try it
even if you are at an age
where you feel like you are very old.
I repeat, this
is only on the ID card,
not in your life.
Your life,
I repeat, is here, above all, and here.
I am at your disposal.
Hello, Xavier, delighted.
I am Reyes.
You said that one of your books
isThe Problem with Being Too Good.
I have two teenage children
who I think are.
When does being good
become a problem?
Well, Reyes, notice that in the consultation
I started exploring this topic
when I realized
that different people were
telling me:
"You know what's wrong, Xavi?
That my problem
is that I'm too good."
And this person told me that,
then another person told me that.
"My colleagues say
I'm too good a person.
At work they tell me I'm too good."  Have they
told you?
I see that yes,
you say yes.
Then, I started exploring.
What does it mean to be too good?
This is where experience
led me to observe
a series of behavioral patterns
that are common
to all these people.
The first
is a sense of duty.
I don't know if you were raised that way,
or if you had parents, father or mother,
who were very strict.
What have they instilled in us?
The sense of duty.
And what is it that one has
that is in one's duty?
Obey.
Therefore, the fundamental principle
of this sense of duty is to obey.  I
remember that at the consultation, not long ago,
when I started writing the book,
a young girl left me frozen
when she told me:
"I don't do anything unless I have to."
"How?"
He says, "I function out of a sense of duty. I
just do what I have to do."
"But then, don't you do what you want?"
"Never."
"But don't you have any desires?"
"Few.
I've been taught since I was little
to do my duty. And I've gotten
so used to it
that I do everything out of duty."
Wow, I was
very surprised because, of course, it
's shocking to see how
far
this first commandment that we
good people receive,
"do your duty," can go.
Comply.
And what is your first compliment?
Obey.  And who should you
obey?
Your parents first.
Then, obey teachers,
obey people,
obey those in charge, obey authority.
Therefore, we have grown up with an order to
do everything well
because it is our duty.
Therefore, the first commandment,
the first order,
of what we would call being too good
is being too obedient.
Because you know that being too obedient
means that, then, I do
n't know how to say no.
That I do everything that is expected,
that I respond
to everything that people want from me,
that I have no limits,
much less for the rest.
Everything is for the rest,
everything is what they ask of me.
Therefore,
this first commandment is already very hard.
But, be careful, there are also exceptions.  It
can also happen that, at home,
and I have also seen this,
cases of people whose
homes were a mess.
Disorder reigned, anarchy reigned,
my parents didn't pay attention to me or anything,
they did what they wanted,
they came in, they went out, they didn't give orders.
So,
some boys and girls have suffered this.  They've
had such a bad time,
they've seen so much chaos
that they've started
organizing themselves from a young age
to be good,
to do everything in an orderly manner.
Then, they grow up in an orderly manner,
even obsessively orderly,
so as not to relive
what made them suffer so much at home,
which was that disorder,
that chaos in which they could not live.
First condition:
being excessively obedient.
The second condition, Reyes,
consists of the command "behave well."
Haven't they told you to "behave"?
And when you're older,
when you're with your parents,
when you leave home,
even though you're 50 years old,
don't they tell you to "be good"?
So, this command, "behave well,"
is a command that indicates, precisely,
not only that you must obey,
but how you must obey.
Then, "behave yourself"
includes life scripts.
And life scripts include:
"Be accommodating,
do everything right,
do everything perfect,
don't cry,
go fast,
please, don't say no."
Therefore, there is
a whole series of orders that the child receives
and that he grows up with,
dragging precisely
these life scripts.  They
are complacent.  They do
everything so that their child,
their children,
their partner,
their family are well.
But notice that a person
who spends his life
pleasing others
comes to a point where he
neglects his own desires.  I
remember a gentleman
who came to the presentation
and said: "I like to be accommodating.
Please don't take that away from me."
"Okay,
if you are happy to please, that's fine.
But do you also ask to be
pleased?"
"Oh, no, not that."
Then, we have a problem.
You give, you give,
but you don't receive,
and that's already very dangerous.
What does it mean?
From so much pleasing, there comes a time when
I become
the eyes of others,
the eyes of my family.
I think some people will
feel reflected in it.
You get home:
"Ugh, this hair, I'll call
the hairdresser to fix it
because you don't wear it very well.
Ugh, son, these shoes... We
need to buy other shoes. We'll
buy new shoes tomorrow."
It's your eyes.  They
see everything.  They
always see everything that is missing.
They see everything that is needed.
They see everything that is necessary
and buy it for you and make it for you.
And there comes a time
when you have to tell them,
"Please, thank you, but I want to do
things my way."
"But, for God's sake,
how can you say that to me?
If I do everything for you."
"Yeah,
you do everything for me, but according to you,
not according to me."
"But if no one
knows what suits you better than me
and knows what's best for you."
Because, in the end, they end up telling you this.
Then, notice how this person has
become disconnected from themselves
and ends up living the life of the other person.
And she ends up living and making the other person live
according to what she considers to be
best for the other person.
And you can't blame him
because, if you do, then he gets angry
because he's doing everything for you.  Do
you realize the extremes
that can be reached
when a person is not only complacent,
but becomes necessary
to the rest of the world?
Therefore, this command to "behave"
can go a long way.
Third commandment:
the impossibility of stopping being good.  You do
n't know how many times
I've told someone in the office:
"But please
tell your boss
that you won't do this job,
that the weekend is yours,
that the rest of your colleagues
have left peacefully
and you've got all the work
just because you don't know how to say no.
Enough, please, nothing will happen.
Tell your boss:
'I won't do it this time.'"
Answer:
"Impossible.
Just thinking about it makes me anxious."
Just thinking about it.
And that is the impossibility
of stopping being good.  That
is, I can't stop obeying,
I have to do what is expected of me,
I have to do things well, I have to
be very punctual, I
have to do it the way they expect it to be done
and, if not, I'm already suffering.
This takes us
into the realm of limits,
and the realm of limits
is a very good terrain to explore.  We
need to learn to set limits
because, if we don't set limits,
then it is others
who will create the life
they want for us.
Setting limits, in the end,
for me, is not about
putting up obstacles,
saying "no" to people.
Setting limits for me
means that you
clearly define yourself in what you want.
But many people are indecisive,
and do you know how they do it?
"I'm sorry."  Haven't
you ever said that?
"I'm sorry.
Of course, on the one hand...
But on the other hand...
On the one hand, I don't want to,
but on the other hand,
if I don't...".
So, I'm always
in the "On the one hand, on the other hand,
on the other hand, on the other hand,
I'm sorry, I'm afraid to disappoint."
And with all this story I don't define myself
and, since I don't define myself,
the rest defines me,
and the rest does what they want with us.
So, here, we're taking it,
we're holding on, we're holding on.
And, after so much patience,
comes the fourth and final point, Reyes.
We finally arrive at the fourth point.
Repressed anger.
What's happening?
After so much holding on, keeping quiet, keeping quiet, holding
on, holding on, holding on, there
comes a day when I can't take it anymore.
Why?
Because I've been repressing the discomforts, I've
been repressing the injustices, I've
been repressing
the desire I had to...
But no, no,
behave yourself, behave yourself, behave yourself.
No, it's my duty, it's my duty.
But there comes a day when you can't take it anymore.
And has it never happened to you
that there is a day
when you can't take it anymore and you just give up?  Has it
ever happened to you
that there comes a day when you have to do the math?
And, when you've done the trick,
doesn't it occur to you that your friends,
the people close to you, look at you and say:
"But what happened to you? It's
not that big of a deal.
But it's just stupid"?
But what happens?
When you've let off steam
and everyone has looked at you
with a "poor" face, "poor",
then you feel guilty.
Then, you realize you've gone too far.
And what are you doing?
Once again inside.  You
know that "behave yourself,
do what they expect you to do
because if you don't, they won't like you."
Imagine having before you a young girl,
30 years old,
of extraordinary beauty,
who, apart from telling me
that she already considered herself old,
on the other hand,
tells you: "When I am me, I don't like it.
On the other hand, when I am what they expect,
then I like it."
So, how is my life?
Always do what others like.
Oysters!
I hope I have given you key clues
and that, from here on, you
can rethink a little what we
call bad kindness.
Hello, Xavier.
It's a pleasure to be here with you.
-Likewise.
-My name is Miguel
and I am now worried
about my children's education.
I want them to be good, to
be obedient,
but I'm afraid they'll be do-gooders,
that they'll say "yes" to everything.
What could you advise me
to avoid this error?
Advising on education
is impossible.
Impossible, I don't dare.
Normally, we
tend to do what has been done to us,
therefore, even if we give advice
and want to give magic formulas,
in the end,
parents get what they have learned
and repeat the same
with their children.
Therefore, it is a joint learning,
children and parents learn continuously.
But, well, let's get to your question.
I remember a training session
and, before the training started,
I went out to have breakfast.
At breakfast I
had a family in front of me.
Father, mother and a little girl,
I would say she was
between 6 and 8 years old, no more.
They made my breakfast bitter,
especially my mother.  It
could have been the father,
in another situation it
would have been the father.
In this case, it was the mother.
The 20 minutes
meant that every minute
this girl received an order.
"Sit still,
don't stand up, don't cross your legs,
now don't touch this,
pick this up with your fork."
They were continuous orders.
Obviously, we can't say,
"Children shouldn't be educated."
Man, of course.
Obviously, they have to learn limits, they
have to learn options, they
have to learn what can be,
what can't be.  Obviously.
In this sense,
if you are an educational parent,
especially if you are a provider parent,
great.
Even better
if you are a facilitating parent.  A
providing father is one who
gives you what you need.  A
facilitating parent is someone who makes it
easier for you to talk,
play together, etc.
Good.  The
only thing I dare to say is:
Plato,
when he
talks about education,
leaves us with a message that is,
for me, fundamental.
"Educating is bringing out from within."
What does it mean?
That this child,
the parents, are skilled enough,
curious and attentive
to what is coming out of their child.
Where he leans,
what he likes, what he wants to try,
what things catch his attention.
Anyone who has more than one child realizes that one wants
one thing and the other wants another.
Even if you educate them the same.
Therefore, there
is something they carry inside,
and this is where we make a mistake if we want to see
children as a blank slate.
Children are like a blank sheet of paper
that needs to be molded,
that needs to be recreated,
and parents are the ones who need to
mold this slate
and write.
No, no, no.
Children are not a blank slate, they
already carry a lot of information.
And this information unfolds
as they live
and encounter situations.
Parents must be careful.
Therefore, the only thing
I dare to say to you, Miguel, is:
be attentive to just observing this.
And, above all, don't want
your children to
be what you want them to be,
try to accompany them
so that they can be who they are.
And what they are
is not something they already have,
it is something that is made
with the information they carry,
and it is something
that will develop over time,
through their experiences,
the media they find,
culture, school,
peers, etc.
If you just did that, it would be fine,
because, unfortunately, parents
think a lot about molding, they
want to mold their son or daughter
in their own image and likeness.  We
don't want to mold our children too much,
but rather accompany them,
better bring them out from within.
And how do I get them out?
Partly, by observing where they lean,
partly, by asking them questions,
partly, by asking them
why they like this,
why they don't like that.
And don't give him a clue, no:
"You must like it",
"But that's silly"...
And you have to take it into account,
not punish him, not take him out of it,
but accompany him
and discover where it's taking him
and to what extent you need to intervene,
but simply to give him clues
so that he can rethink what he's
going through.  I believe
this task
is impossible today
because we live
in a culture of performance
where there is no time for anything.
Then, we immediately put them
in the dynamics of rush,
performance, we
put them in our culture.
That's why
I believe that being a parent today
takes incredible courage.
Incredible.
With enormous courage.  I'm
not surprised
that the figures that have come out recently
tell us that there are
fewer and fewer people who want to have children,
because it really is a vocation,
a dedication.
But it is a commitment that,
at the same time, makes you grow a lot.
Children, sons, are a great mirror
for your own life.
Therefore, we want to educate them
and, deep down,
they end up educating us.
Hello, Xavier, how are you?
I am Maria.
I've realized
that being good doesn't always end up being useful.
Can evil goodness exist?
Of course.
In fact, my colleague
and beloved teacher Antoni Bolinches
was the one who gave me the clue
about the expression "mala bondat".  I
remember that at a conference we
were with different colleagues,
and he, at one point,
cited an aspect of people
and said: "And this is
the practice of bad kindness.
When a person
does everything to be loved
and does everything for the rest,
harming themselves,
this is the practice
of bad kindness."
So, when does bad kindness exist?
When, indeed,
I give, what we've been saying all along,
but, on the other hand, what I receive is not...
Not in benefit, I
don't want to speak in benefit,
but, for me, it's a detriment.  I end up
feeling bad, they
make fun of me, I
don't feel good, I
always go home thinking
that I'm too good.
Then, I tried to define,
gathering information
that I had from other authors, I
tried to explain,
also briefly, with four ideas,
what this too-good person is,
that is,
the practitioner of bad kindness.
The first is rigidity,
the rigidity with which
one treats oneself.
"I'm good to everyone,
but I don't treat myself well. I
'm very rigid to myself, I
treat myself badly, I put a
lot of pressure on myself, I
demand a lot of myself."
Then, a person who is
excessively demanding of themselves,
very perfectionist,
a person who always bases
everything on moral mandates:
do good, do good,
do nothing wrong, do good...
This person, in the end,
ends up acting in a rigid way.
I repeat, especially for herself.  She
is able to put up with everyone,
but she can't put up with herself.
The second behavior
is anticipatory anxiety.
What does a neurotic person do?
But so does the person who is too good.
Always anticipate
everything that may happen.
And why should it be anticipated?
Because he has to control everything.
And why does he have to control everything?
So that nothing goes wrong.
"Because, if I fail, I'll feel terrible, and
, if I feel terrible, I'm not good,
and, if I'm not good, I'm bad."
Oysters!
Therefore, this...
this suffering ahead of time,
this anguish
that anticipates everything that can happen,
that makes you prepare,
that makes you strive... I have
n't said it before,
but one of the keys to "behaving well",
which is going very well for us now, is effort.
"Make an effort."
A good person,
a person who anticipates everything,
is a person who does everything through effort.
Imagine a person
who tells you, as they told me,
a person who tells you:
"Me, if things don't cost me a lot, they
have no value to me.
If they don't cost a lot, they have no value.
In other words, it has to cost me a lot. I
have to suffer, it has to cost me."
To be like King Sisyphus,
who is always climbing that mountain
and, when he reaches the top, he falls back down
and spends all eternity
climbing up and down the mountain.
Oysters!  What anguish, what suffering!
The third cause would be the ability
to harm yourself.
But, well, I've already
more or less developed this
when I said that bad kindness is this,
the ability to do things
that, ultimately, harm you.
But the fourth point,
which would have a lot to do with this one,
is the impossibility
of being in the face of conflict.  I ca
n't stand conflict.  I
can't stand being in a situation
where someone might get upset,
get angry, get upset,
pick a fight with me,
argue with me... Oh, how lazy!  I
don't want you to raise your hand, I'm
not going to ask you to raise your hand,
but I'm sure
many of you would raise your hand
if I asked: Do you like conflict?
No!  Do
you feel comfortable
with conflict?  No!  Do
you want to avoid conflict?  Yes!
When conflict,
in reality, is nothing more
than putting our differences on the table
or face to face,
how different we are,
the different ways of seeing things.
Conflict helps us grow.
Conflict is necessary
to get to know each other better.
Conflict
is necessary to grow together.
If not, what should we do?  Swallow it all?
Always say amen to everything?
In order to avoid conflict, do I
let everything pass?
So, where are the limits?
Where is my dignity
if I immediately let everything go?
If I don't care about my things
because "it doesn't matter, whatever you want.
"Whatever you want, love".
Then,
a dialogue of the deaf occurs.
Because, in the end, what
the conflict tries to put into play
is what I need,
what is important,
and where the limits are.
And that's why we have to talk.
And that's why, when we say:
"Love, I need to talk to you,
we have a pending conversation",
everyone already...
This "we have to talk"... Oh!
Because we can already see a conflict coming.
But it is necessary.
And, as before, better. We
have to face the conflict.
Well, María, I hope you are doing very well.
Hello, Xavier, thank you very much.
My name is Rubén and, well,
as a child of a generation
of new technologies, we
often think
that we can master everything with a click.
And, of course, we
want to have everything under control.
Well, well, how do we keep things going
when chance or unforeseen events
throw our lives out of whack?
Look, me, when I was young,
a little younger than you,  I
remember that I liked to
have a full schedule.
But full. In other
words, my anxiety,
my feeling of emptiness
was seeing a gap in my schedule.
And I had scheduled
visits with my close friends,
dates, whatever, I
had everything scheduled.
But what happened?
When the day came,
because I scheduled it
a month or two in advance,
when the day came, I didn't feel like it.
Or that day
something more interesting came up.
Then, I realized
that wanting to control
life is impossible.
Or, better said, control
ends up controlling us.
So, that's a paradox.
But I'll explain it to you with a metaphor.
But, before, it came
to my mind while I was telling you... I'm getting
carried away again.
The movie, I don't know if you've seen it,
by Marvel,Doctor Strange. In
Doctor Strange
there's a moment when the old woman, I
won't spoil it, the old woman,
who is with Doctor Strange,  He says to him:
"Do you want me to tell you what the secret
of existence, of life is?"
He says: "Okay."
"Nothing is about you."
Life is not about you.
This does not depend on you.
Therefore, this idea
that we have to control everything
and fight so that everything is as we want it to be
is the craziest thing we can imagine. That is
why God laughs at our plans. He
laughs because, in the end,
whatever has to happen will happen.
In reality, we control very little.
So, how do we learn to live
with the minimum control,
the just and necessary only,
so that I can avoid the most immediate?
But, controlling life,
controlling the rest, that is madness.
My teacher
sometimes used a metaphor,
which was that of the butterfly.
He said that, if you extend your hand
and let the butterfly
land on your hand,
and you do not control it, you
do not close it, you do not want to catch it,
if you let it be, let it be:
"let it be", let it be, it
will be there as long as it wants,
and as long as it is  there, enjoy it.
And when it wants to leave, it will leave.
But when you want to control it,
what you will do is kill it.
You will probably be left
without a butterfly
because it will fly away
or because you will kill it.
Therefore, control is
an issue that we have to solve.
But the basis of control is fear.
Because I am afraid, I control.
Because I realize
that control is not enough, I have
anxiety,
and when I suffer from anxiety,
in the end I end up becoming an obsessive. It
is a journey that we take
when the basis is in fear,
and fear must be quickly removed
.
So, I will
give you all a little metaphor
for you to think about.
A master and his disciple
are on their way to the monastery
so that the disciple
can become a master. It is
getting dark,
they find a small lost house
and knock on the door: "Hello, we are monks,
we are going to the monastery, would
you mind
if we eat here at the house?"
"Yes, yes,
you can stay here at the  house".
Well, they see that it is a family,
father, mother and two children. They
dress very simply,
very poorly.
And the teacher asks him:
"What do you live on?".
"We live because we have a cow,
which gives us what we need:
we have milk, it gives us cheese,
and that is what we have for dinner,
cheese and milk, and that is what we do with it".
"Ah, very good".
The next day they return on the road
and the teacher says to the disciple:
"Go to the house and,
when they don't see you, take the cow away".
The story says "throw it away",
but I don't want to be so cruel.
But: "Take the cow away".
"Man, teacher, this cannot be,
for the love of God,
that these people will die
that we will leave them
without food". "Listen to me".
Well, he listened to him.
15 years passed, 15 years later,
the boy, when he left the monastery,
already a teacher,
the first thing that came to his mind  What he had to do
was go to the house
where they had spent that night,
convinced that he would find nothing,
that those people must be dead.
And, instead, he found
the opposite: a luxurious house,
not luxurious, but very well-kept,
a beautiful house,
with colors, there was a garden, there were
flowers, plants...
"Well, they must be others".
He knocked on the door:
"Listen, look,
I'm a teacher who comes from the monastery,
where we spent a night...".
"Ah, yes, I remember."
"Man, but that has changed a lot.
But how did you change all this?".
"Well, look, I'll explain it to you.
It turns out that one day the cow left.
From the day the cow left, we
had to be smart.
We had to sell
the tools we had,
with the tools
we bought things to plant,
we planted,
from the planting we took out plants
and things to sell,
we sold it and we started doing business,
and now we can live
peacefully from all this".
"Ah, very good, very good,
thank you very much", and he left.
And he left thinking the same thing
that I will ask you:
which is the cow
that I will not let go of in my life?
Which is the cow that, if I let it go, I would
be terribly afraid of?
Because, if I do not let go,
the one that I do not let go will
always have me,
and the one that has me has control over me.
Therefore, the sooner you
let go of control, the better.
Hello, Xavier, I am Esteban.
Nice to meet you. Are
kindness
and sincerity linked?
And how can we be kind
without stopping being sincere?
Wow! What a
question you are asking me, Esteban.
Look, now that I have quoted my teacher, I will tell
you something
that he told us  usually.
The foundation of personal confidence
is built
on two pillars.
The first pillar is the ability
to show myself as I am.
"This is me, I want you to know me.  I
don't care, that's how I am".
This is where
the attitude of authenticity appears,
which we sometimes
also call "spontaneity".
But this is only one column.
The other column is the column of:
and the rest, do they want to listen to me?
And the rest, do they want to know about me?
And the rest, are they
interested in what I say? Do I
know if it's the right time
to say and speak sincerely?
Is it the time
for me to show myself as I am
or maybe now is not
the time to show myself?
Then,
notice that these two columns
are the ones that support
personal security.
If I have a
lot of self-confidence
and I'm a very extroverted person
and, therefore, I don't have any quirks,
and I do this:
"I tell people what I think to their faces
and, if they like it,
fine, and, if not, [ __ ] them". Do
you consider
that a trustworthy person?
Then, he is a person
who practices "sincericide". He
doesn't think about the rest.
When I am able to manage
in a sustained manner
and from my decision,
to decide what I show, what I don't show,
I can show myself as I am,
but I also measure how far I have to show
because I don't know what the rest want, I
don't know what the rest need, I
don't know if it's the right place.
Therefore, if I
don't know how to control myself in this sense, I will
fall into this reactive spontaneity.
Small children
are tremendously spontaneous.
But there
is a little bit of everything in their spontaneity.
They are proactive: "Look at what a
nice detail he had".
"Look at what he told me, how funny".
But this same child,
a while later, is reactive,
has tantrums,
cries, shouts, insults, even.
Oh my!
This reactive spontaneity
is something that a person
who matures learns to manage.
I manage my immediacy.
When a person
doesn't know how to manage their immediacy, they
can fall into a
mechanical and reactive spontaneity.
Therefore, Esteban,
I would tell you that the only way we have to be
able to consider the  The
issue of sincerity
is, first,
seeing to what extent
I have the ability to show myself, I do
n't have difficulties,
but if at the same time I know how to contain myself,
if at the same time I know how to distinguish when it's
time to do it or not to do it.
Okay?
Hi, Xavier. I'm Graciela. We
spend too much time
regretting decisions we've made:
"What if I had done this?  What
if I hadn't done it?",
as you said before.
We get into a loop
and forget the decisions
we have to make now
and we forget to be in the present.
Could you tell us about this
heavy feeling that is guilt? I
need the whole program.
Well, let's talk about guilt, okay.
You used an expression
that I really liked,
which is "heavy".
Guilt immediately takes us
to the past
and, without a doubt,
it is a heavy weight of the past.
Therefore, guilt,
which is always
the moral conscience,
which is how we value,
look at and act on what happens to us, what
happens to others,
what we should do,
always has a lot to do
with moral conscience. I'll
give you a case.
A man comes to the consultation. He tells
me that he lost a business
that was probably a very good business.
And that he had doubts, he was hesitating,
thinking, should I do it or not...
And, in the midst of his doubts,
those who made the offer have
already sold it to someone else.
And, when  he wanted to make up his mind, they told him:
"The deal is done."
Well, he felt terrible. He
felt very regretful, as you say.
And he comes to the consultation and tells me about it.
And I say to him:
"But we can solve this,
more or less.
A couple of days
of getting your head around it and that's it."
He says: "No, Xavier,
that's not the problem.
The problem is
that this happened seven years ago.
And I can't do it anymore."
So, here we see two
different movements of guilt.
One movement is before acting
and the other movement is after acting.
Many people blame themselves for regret,
which is usually people
who don't do what they planned to do. That is
, what do I regret?
What I didn't do.
What do I regret?
What I should have done. We
regret that.
There is an excellent work
by an author,
because she is not a psychologist,
but an economist,
who later dedicated herself to palliative care
and wrote a very interesting book
about the things that
people regret before dying.
And, look at it, how funny,
that one of the biggest regrets
is not having lived the life that I wanted.
But, you see?, it is a regret.
I regret what I haven't done.
However, with respect to what I have already done,
another heavy weight appears.
And this heavy weight
is personal bitterness,
which  we would say, not remorse,
but when I am
already suffering deeply
and there is a resentment
that we call remorse. It
is different.
Repentance,
remorse.
Then, when I have remorse,
I have a heavy weight inside
that I cannot get rid of
because my insides are boiling,
because I cannot get it off my chest,
because the guilt has
become something
that the person I was
working with,
the one from seven years old,
becomes an expression
that we call "moral masochism".
Can a person be
so cruel,
hate themselves so much,
that they reach this point
of moral masochism?
What is it like to constantly beat themselves up
for something
that happened once in their life?
Well, yes.
There are people who live morality,
who take this moral conscience
to this extreme.
I hope it is not yours.
Then, this remorse
is always for what we have done.
"But how did it come to me?
Why did I do it?
My God, I can't pull back, I can't
go back.  I ca
n't solve it anymore."
Notice what two powerful figures
there are under this layer
that we call "guilt."
If we look for its meaning in guilt,
we will see that,
in reality, it has no meaning.
But, to look for a functionality for it,
I have to go to a philosopher, Hume,
who spoke about moral sentiment.
And Hume tells us:
"Guilt, this feeling of guilt,
we use before acting
to know
how we would feel if we did this.
And, because sometimes we feel that
if we do this it will go wrong,
because sometimes
we feel that this will not be right, we do
not do it".
Therefore,
there is a certain moral functionality
in this sense.
Before I regret it
or before I feel guilty,
I already feel
that this does not feel right in me,
therefore, it is better not to do it.
This would be the cautious sense, it would be
the precaution, it would be
the moral sense
that we can attribute to guilt.
What is its purpose?
To make you think
about the consequences of your actions.
And that is good.
Now, does it have any other kind of utility?
No.
Why?
Because I want to believe that,
both you and all of you here,
when you did what you did,
it was the only thing you could do
at that moment, it
was the only thing that fit
in your conscience,
it was the only thing you knew how to do.
If you had had
other behaviors,
other visions,
other ways of doing things available, you
would have done them already.
But, when you did what you did, it
was because at that moment it
seemed to you
that  It was what you had to do. There is
no blame.
Only responsibility
for the consequences
of what you did.
And this should not be included in blame, it
should be included in responsibility.
"Responsibility"
comes from the Latin "respondere",
which means "to respond, to
give an answer".
When I talk about "responsibility",
I do not mean "to take charge of",
"to load with".
"Responsibility"
for me is "to respond".
So,
in the face of what I have done, I respond.
And I respond as I have to respond
because it is my responsibility.
Therefore, I do
not have to worry about feeling...
"Why did I do it?
Why did I do it?"
I did it because it was
the only thing I could do. Let's
take a person who is dead passionate about
marrying someone who
everyone can see is going to be a disaster.
Everyone can see it.
And not everyone can, but many people say to him:
"Why don't you think about it for a while?"
"Don't be in a hurry."
"Get to know each other a little better."
"No, I'm getting married.
That I have never experienced
what I am experiencing.
That I am crazy with passion.
Who is the love of my life.  I'm getting
married".
Well, nothing, let's all go to the wedding.
And what happens?
Well, what everyone saw coming.
A disaster. They
don't even make it half a year.
Then,
you take this person and tell them:
"It's your fault.
You screwed up.  You did
n't notice, we told you so.
We told you very clearly:
'Wait.'"
But, for him,
who was crazy with love, with passion,
these speeches, these stories did
not fit in his consciousness.
In his consciousness, all that fit was:
"I love this woman."
Or "this man," whatever.
And that's it.
Then he realizes it.
Then he learns the lesson.
Ah, but this is the good part.
If I am responsible,
now I also have to be honest and say:
"Thanks to what happened to me,
today I have a skill
or I have a point of view,
a belief, an experience
that allows me to have
more options available to me."
But why do I have them available now?
Because this happened.
So, in the end, I
almost have to thank him.
Then, there can be no guilt
when the intention you have is positive, it
is good for itself
and, moreover, nothing else fits in his mind.
And, perhaps, he has to go
through this experience in order to learn.
So,
count when the guilt  we become
something that we have to carry,
something that we have to drag,
which is a heavy weight
that, moreover, does not solve anything for me
because the repentant learns the lesson.
"I regret it, I will never do it again".
"I'm sorry, I regret it, I will
not do it again".
On the other hand, guilt does not.
Guilt always leaves you
with a weight hanging over you,
and that will not help you
grow as a person.
But what is the problem? And I'm done.
If there is guilt, there is fear of punishment.
And, if there is fear of punishment,
either I fear what may happen to me
or I end up punishing myself, I
beat myself up
because it is how I atone, how I pay
the punishment for the guilt that I have.
Therefore, it is better not to blame, it is
better to be responsible.
Hi, Xavier, my name is Lucas.
Look, I have a problem.
Well, I have many,
but one of the problems that I have
is that, sometimes, I think too much.
And here we have been commenting
that we are immersed in routine,
which  we don't do what we like,
but what we have to do
and we are always making decisions.
And, in fact, right now, I have just
finished my degree
and I have to decide
what I want to do with my life,
the big question.
So, what would you say to us
about the importance
of knowing ourselves
and, above all, how can we know ourselves better?
Okay, first I'll solve your problem
of having a lot of problems. We
don't have a lot of problems.
Generally, we have a problem
that we have everywhere.
Then, when you solve
that problem, everything is solved.
Well, it's true, in the temple of Delphi
there are two big inscriptions.
One says: "Know yourself"
and the other says: "Nothing in excess".
This means that the people
who went to the temple of Delphi
were people who
went to see the oracle,
who were priestesses,
who today would be tarot readers,
but, surely, with another
kind of deep knowledge
about human wisdom
and the wisdom of the cosmos.
And, as an oracle,
people  wanted to know his fate.
Back then, “know thyself”
was like, “Don’t come asking for the moon.
If you come to ask,
first know yourself.
Be aware of your limits,
be aware of your humanity.  Do
n't ask us for impossible things."
Why? Because you have to recognize
your humility.
And being "humble" is "humus", "earth",
and the "earth" is "we are from here".
We are not from heaven, we are not gods.
I distinguish self-knowledge
from personal development.
Personal development,
or personal growth, we
can call it that,
has the mission of
improving our character, of
becoming people who can resolve
certain aspects
of our personality,
but always without leaving the issue
of our character, in some way.
On the other hand, self-knowledge leads us
to go beyond the character.
"Ep, who are you really?".
"Knowing yourself"
is finding your essentiality in yourself,
finding who you really are. We
all want to know this.
But, because we have confused ourselves
with the character,
with the personality we have,
we believe that we are this
and, in reality, we are not this.
This is only the format, it is
only the character. I do
n't know if you know it,
but in the old  In Greece,
the mask was called "person".
What was the person? The mask.
Therefore, it is like saying:
"All people,
in reality, are like masks
of the archetypes
of those forms that,
historically, come from long ago
and that are the molds that have built
our personalities".
This is reflected very well
when we operate from the law of the mirror,
or the law of reflection,
which I like to call it.
"As is outside, so is inside,
as is above, so is below".
Therefore,
to know myself,
I must be able to see
what my reflection is like in the world, what my reflection is like
with divinity, what
my reflection is like with wisdom,
with knowledge.
Because, when I confront myself
with my own mirror,
I realize where I am, I realize where I am going
and I realize to what extent I am going on the
path of my essence or not. I
tell you all this because... I will
give you a very simple,
very practical example.
When I  I was younger,
older than you,
the archetype they attributed to me
was that of the "vagrant".
"You're like a vagrant".
I was the vagrant because I didn't stop. I
was always doing things, I didn't stop.
Back then, I was the vagrant.
A little older,
when I started
working in the theater and all that,
then I was already the "character".
So,
I think that my time as an actor,
my time in the theater,
radio, this whole world,
is the time when I was,
perhaps, more of a character.
Less of me and more of a character.
Until recently,
if I told you
what the reflection in the mirror was, I would
tell you that this reflection
was the priest.
They say: "You look like a rector.  "
Sometimes you talk
and move like you're a priest."
Do you know what they said to me yesterday?
"You're like my grandfather.  And
I loved him so much.  He
was such a wise man."
Then, of course, now I am,
apart from Snowflake, according to some,
"the wise grandfather."
I am not all of these characters.
No one, no vagabond, no character...
I am none of these.
But there are aspects of me
that are reflected to the rest
in such a way that they recognize them
as if I were that.
But the million-dollar question is:
but are you that?
So,
this is where we go to the temple of Delphi.
This is where we go to the beginning
of "know thyself."
And this is where Socrates,
when he accompanies the young Alcibiades,
who wants to devote himself to politics,
asks him:
"You, young man,
who wants to dedicate yourself to politics, do you
know yourself?
Because, if we know ourselves,
at least we will have something resolved."
Then, Socrates says to him:
"What does it mean to
know oneself?"
Then, he says:
"Just as one discovers the eye
through the gaze,
because one looks and, when one realizes it, says:
'Ah, I have an eye', he
says: 'We recognize
our essence
when we become a mirror,
when our soul acts as a mirror
with wisdom and with divinity.'"
Then,
here he gives us a fundamental key:
the knowledge of what
reality is and how it is.
And the knowledge of reality
is knowing the cosmos, it
is knowing the universe, it
is knowing what life is made of.
Then,
I must approach this wisdom
that helps me to know
the invisible threads that move everything,
and this is approaching, in some way,
a knowledge that gives me wisdom
and that is available,
because this knowledge has been transmitted by
all the spiritual
and religious traditions of the  world.
Today quantum physics does it.
Therefore,
when you become a mirror with wisdom,
you learn what life is like,
but when you look towards the divine,
then, you
find your soul, you find yourself.
What you are looking for is within you,
but this must be found.
And how do you find it?
When you empty yourself.
This emptying yourself of yourself,
precisely, is to remove
all these twists and turns that you give it:
"If I am, if I am not,
if I am this character,
if I am that other character,
if I am this way,
if I am in another way".
You forget about this
and go into silence.
Hence the success that meditation has now,
because they are paths
that help us to go deeper,
to, in some way, displace from within
this part that we have identified
as "ego" or as "me"
and that, at the same time,
allows us to discover what is there.
Therefore, what you are looking for, beloved, you
already are.
You are. It's
just a matter of looking for it, okay?
Hi, Xavier, I'm Adrián.
Thank you for sharing your knowledge
and experience with us.
Thank you, Adrián.
Groucho Marx said with humor:
"These are my principles
and, if you don't like them, I have others."
And you tell us:
"These are your beliefs,
these are your feelings
and, if not, you can change them."
But how do we make changes that are so deep
and so deeply rooted in us
successfully?
Yes, there are two things here
that we can clarify.
Groucho Marx talked
about the relativism of things.
"If everything is relative, what does it matter
whether you believe one thing or another?
What does it matter if you like
one thing or another?
What does it matter?
If everything is the same, if everything is equal.
If it's the same, I have this
and I also have the other thing.
I have this and I also have the opposite".
Of course, this, of course,
is a relativism that hurts.
People have principles,
values
that shape our character
and that, in some way,
direct and guide our lives.
Therefore, the most important task
from the personality level
is to make character, to make yourself.
To make yourself, you
will need to build a house
with beliefs that are useful to you,
not with limiting beliefs,
with beliefs that give you life,
that develop your abilities.
Therefore, what you believe
is creating the reality that you will live. That is
why
beliefs are so important.
Therefore,
not all beliefs are valid.
People are valid,
but their beliefs
are points of view.
Each person has a
different way of seeing reality,
and it is their way, it
is their reality.
What is it that matters to us?
Whether this reality makes you happy or not.
Which beliefs are the ones
that make us grow
and which beliefs
limit our existence?
How certain are my beliefs?
To what extent do I believe what I
believe because it is something
I have experienced,
something I have lived
and, therefore, I have
come to this conclusion?
"A dog bit me:
dogs are dangerous".
"When did it bite you?".
"When I was 10".
"How old are you now?". "60".
"And you still believe the same?".
"Of course, dogs are dangerous".
So what does it mean?
That experience makes me believe
that the belief is true,
and I support myself by things that have happened
and that I have lived in the past,
but that do not allow me to
update in the present.
Therefore, what I believe
must be validated
and must be updated continuously.
This seems to go against
this opinion that many people have
that changing your mind
is something to turn a blind eye to,
something that should not be done.
"If you change your mind a lot,  "It's
that you don't know what you want." Do you
remember Eduard Punset,
who was a minister
and later became a science communicator?
I participated
in one of his programs,
inRedes,on television,
and Punset,
in one of his books, said:
"Many scientists have shown
that being intelligent is
having the ability to
quickly change your opinion or belief
if you realize that you are wrong."
It is a symptom of intelligence to
change your opinion when the other person
or the circumstances prove you are right.
On the other hand, we
come from a very obstinate culture
that seems to have taught us
that this is enshrined in law
and cannot be changed,
and that, if you change,
it means that you are not very well.
Therefore, how important is it to
be aware of what beliefs
are building my life,
but also what beliefs I need to
change in my life
because they are not helping me, I
am not growing,
I am always living the same.
And why do I always live the same?
Because I always think the same.
Antonio Blay, who  was
a great transpersonal psychologist, he
said that we,
fundamentally, are three things,
intelligence, love and energy:
the ability to think, the ability to feel
and the ability to do things.
So, to
update yourself is, precisely, to
update these three potentials.
Not, on the contrary, to
get stuck in beliefs.
Beware of wanting to be
right as everyone else.
Discover for yourself,
update yourself continuously
and be able
to change your beliefs
and the things in your life. You will
only find one problem,
which is what you detect in me,
which is: "It's very hard to change".
Why is it very hard to change?
Because I have been programmed
for a long time.
Being programmed for a long time
means that my neural networks
have already been building
a series of habits.
And these habits
are already automations,
so that, sometimes,
when I feel something that I feel,
I think I feel it because it happens to me.
And it is true that it happens to you,
but it doesn't happen to you because of what is happening, it happens to
you because it is your programming.
And here we have a problem. We
feel emotions in the present,
but they belong to the past. That's
why, if you look at it,
faced with the same situations,
you feel, think
and act in the same way. What does that
mean?
What are you programmed to do?
So,
a human life that lives on automatic
is a life where there is nothing
that is by itself. It
is a life where you have
become a robot.
What do I do with this
if it is something that prevents me from growing?
Therefore, an old wise man, Gurdjieff,
a spiritual master, said:
"We believe that we
decide our life
and that we are
the general director of what we live.
In reality,
we are the stewards of our unconscious."
Therefore, everything we have automated,
everything we bring here is recorded
and will appear, and will continue to appear. That's
why I always ask... I'm done. I
always ask...
Please, the first impression.
Don't stay
with the first impression you have
because the old will always come to you, the
automatic will always come to you, the
usual will always come to you.
Be able to realize it:
this is the old, but what do I want?
Where do I want to direct it?
And what meaning do I want to give to this?
Because, if I don't renew this, I will
live a robotic life,
I will be an automaton
and only at the gates of death, will
Hello, Xavier, enchanted.
I'm Aroa. You
dedicate one of your books
to communication,
to this very complex system
that we humans have created
to communicate.
What idea could you share
with us to understand each other better?
Probably
the most difficult thing in this world
is to be yourself and to be yourself with others. I
don't know if you agree with me.
And, above all,
something that has
a lot to do with communication,
which is to show yourself.
Surely, one of the things
that I am asked the most in the consultation
is precisely this fear,
shame, difficulty in showing myself.
And today, that we live in a culture
that is the culture of showing oneself,
because we are showing ourselves,
it is the culture that we live in,
a narcissism, but galloping.
Well, here comes an interesting question:
what is it that I am afraid to show
when I say that I am afraid to show myself to others? In
other words,
what do I think
others will see if I show myself?
What scares me so much? What am I
so afraid of if I show myself?
So, generally,
what is difficult for us to show ourselves
is our vulnerability.
There is an author named John Powell
who wrote a book that says:
"Why am I afraid to tell you who I am?"
And the answer is: "I am afraid to tell you
who  I am because it's the only thing I have".
Oh my!
So,
if all I have is the feeling
that I have something kept inside me
that I don't want the rest to know
because it's something of mine, it
's as if the rest of us had the ability
to look inside me
and see that.
In the end, this fear of showing ourselves
leads us to vulnerability.
So, notice that there is
an extraordinary relationship
between not showing who I am
because I would be ashamed
and what would make me ashamed is for you to
see how vulnerable I am.
So, this is
when we begin to interrupt what
would be the flow of a relationship,
both with myself,
with the rest of us and with a group,
because I fear
that these things will happen to me.
What things can happen to me?
The three great fears
of the moral conscience, the
three great fears of this little one
that I have inside me.
What is he afraid of?
That he will be shamed,
that he will be blamed
and, above all, that he will be rejected.
Then,
feeling that someone will  can reject
is a terrible experience
for human beings.
Keep in mind
that we come from a tribal era,
we come from an evolution
in which the tribe had a lot of power,
and anyone expelled from the tribe,
any person expelled from the tribe
was certain death
because they had no protection, they were left
unprotected
against animals, the climate, etc.
Therefore, there is a human fear, which is
the fear of rejection,
and because I don't feel rejected
or fear rejection, I
close myself off, I don't explain, I
only explain part of it,
and this greatly complicates communication
because what is communication? It
is the vehicle that allows
you and I to be able to unite,
that allows you and I to know each other,
that allows you and I to
share things.
If there is no communication,
there is no relationship,
therefore, what is the fundamental basis
of communication?
Knowledge, on the one hand,
and relationship, on the other.
These are the two keys
that all communication pursues,
sharing information,
some knowledge,
but,  at the same time, to unite, to link,
that there is
a connection between us.
When
communication experts meet
in Palo Alto, California, in the 70s, they
come to the conclusion
that we cannot not communicate,
that, in reality, everything is communication.
Therefore,
the problem is not communication.
When we say: "This couple
has a communication problem",
"What we lack
is communication".
No, no, no, we
always have communication.
Communication always exists,
we do what we do,
even if we don't talk to each other.
If we don't talk to each other,
there is also communication.
Silence is communication,
not wanting to look at you is communication,
everything is communication.
Therefore, we
don't have communication problems, we have
relationship problems, we
have problems
interpreting codes in which you speak
and with which you understand your world
and I understand mine,
and here, speaking, people don't understand each other, they don't
understand each other because it's not enough.
In order to be understood,
I have to encode very well
how you are encoding your reality,
how you think  what you think
and feel what you feel.
And if I can't get close... We
call this "empathy".
If I can't get close to you,
to this knowledge, I
won't connect with you. It
's not enough to talk to understand each other.
The language we have to speak
is the language of what's behind:
what's behind the words,
what's behind
what you want to convey to me...
And this requires a relationship with you from me,
and this requires
a certain degree of empathy from me.
We use the word "empathy"
very lightly.
"No, we have to be more empathetic".
"You have to put yourself in the other person's shoes".
But putting yourself in the other person's shoes
is very complicated.
And, in addition, it requires,
on my part, silence
and the ability to enter into your world.
And when you enter
empathetically into the other person's world,
that's when you can say to them:
"If I were in your shoes, I
would do exactly the same thing as you."
That's  empathize.
"If I were in your shoes, I would
suffer like you."
"If I were in your shoes,
I would think like you."
Why?
Because that is putting myself in your shoes. It
is another thing if I agree with it,
but I don't agree with it.
But putting myself in your shoes is that. And we
don't do this exercise,
among other things,
because today we are in a hurry
and we don't pay attention to what we call
the space proper to the relationship,
and we don't listen carefully,
and we don't make space.
And, when we do it,
we have to practice
something called "assertiveness."
Being assertive costs a lot,
therefore,
certain instruments or methodologies must be used, of which
we have many today,
such as assertiveness,
so that I speak in the first person
and can ask you,
can tell you what I need.
What I believe, what I feel.
That is why the English
use "I" for everything.
"I feel, I think, I believe."
I believe, I feel, I do.
In  change, here,
when you use the "I" a lot,
you are suspicious.
"A lot of 'I', a
lot of 'I', a lot of 'I' here".
But I am not the one who feels, I
am not the one who speaks, I
am not the one who believes, I am not the one who...? I
have to speak from myself
and I have to speak to you in the first person.
"Look, I don't like it, I feel bad
when you shake your head at me.
Please don't refuse me, I'm
begging you."
But I feel bad, I
don't say to you: "Don't refuse me!".
Then, here too, we are very much of the "you".
"Because you, because you, because you...".
The fault is always the other.
Then, no, the practice
of assertiveness is necessary,
the practice of empathy is necessary,
non-violent communication,
which helps us to pay attention
to the need of the other.
Not only in what they think,
in what they feel, but:
"Okay, you see it one way,
I see it another way".
But behind
everything we complain,
there is some unmet need.
Then, when we talk, when we
show ourselves, we have to
go there,
so that I can share with you what
I think, what I feel
and what I need.
And what do I expect from you?
That you welcome me with empathy
and that you also return to me assertively
what you believe,
what you think and what you  you need.
And in this meeting we agree on things.
And this is possible
because we communicate.
There are three viruses
that will always appear in a conversation,
with anyone,
which are omissions,
distortions and generalizations.
This will always happen.
When I talk to you I
have to be careful
because you will make omissions and so will I.
What does it mean to omit?
There are things that I don't explain,
not because I don't want to explain them,
but because I don't remember them.
Simply, because I get home:
"How was lunch?" "Very good".
"Did you have a good time?" "Yes". We will
also distort things,
then the presuppositions come:
"No, I presuppose
that what you wanted to tell me...",
"I misunderstood you
because I thought you wanted to".
Misunderstandings
always come from presuppositions.
Presupposing doesn't help,
nor does generalizing help:
"All men are the same",
"You always, you always",
"I never, never".
Then, "never",
"always",  "everyone", "everyone"... You
have to be careful
because these languages
are complicated communication.
Therefore: "Wow,
how difficult it is to
relate to others,
how easy it would be
if life were just me doing what I want,
how easy it would be if I drove alone,
because everyone else is a nuisance,
everyone drives badly,
everyone does it badly, everyone
happens when they shouldn't happen".
"How nice that I'll have a good time alone",
but, when four days had passed, I would say:
"How lonely I am, I
miss you,
I wish you were here".
Therefore, we already need relationships,
and to relate well we
need communication,
and to communicate well we
have to be able to show ourselves
as we are.
Here's the whole game, okay?
Hi, Xavier, I'm Almudena.
In terms of relationships, I
notice
that I have fewer conversations
with people I love.
Friends who used to call me on the phone
now only send me memes. I've
also noticed
that, at my house,  My children
sometimes write me WhatsApp messages
from their room
to ask me something.
How can we fall in
love with words again?
When I wrote the book
about communication...
This book was 20 years ago.
Look, Almudena, I would never have imagined
that 20 years later I
would be talking about this.
I thought that things would improve,
that we would be more skilled
in the art of communication,
relationships, that we would have learned
about emotional intelligence,
that we would already be people
who would have perfectly understood
what it is to be human.
I would never have imagined
that I would have to rewrite the book
and that I would have to explain
what I am explaining now,
which is that it can even be an invasion
to be called on the phone.
Today it is in bad taste, it
is bad manners to call on the phone
because it is an interruption.
"Ep, why are you calling me?
I'm in my world,
with my own things, I
'm doing... Why are you calling me?
Send me a message".
Then, this then translates
into the fact that many current generations
fear in-person situations.
The other day a baker was telling me this, she says:
"Young people don't come to buy bread
because they don't know what to ask for, they don't
know what to do". It
's a social situation that they don't experience.
Why don't we face things, why is
n't there face-to-face contact? Why are
n't we able to
go to public places
and do things with people?
Because we get frustrated.
And what is frustrated?
What we want to do.
What is frustrated?
Realizing that I lack tools.
Experiencing things that I don't want to experience.
Then, we
find ourselves facing a society
that I would almost call
"the society of frustration".
Frustration in this sense, understood
as low tolerance for frustration. I don't get anxious
for anything,
I get frustrated
for nothing,
if things aren't the way I want them,
I get tense.
If things aren't the way I want them, I
even get aggressive.
We are  witnessing
many social situations
in which there is aggression.
Aggression against teachers,
aggression against doctors,
there is a lot of aggression, and you say:
"And where does this come from?"
Because people can't stand it, they
can't stand waiting, they
can't stand having
things said to their child, they
can't stand certain conditions, they can't
stand it.
Not standing means
low tolerance for frustration.
And the answer is
a tense, aggressive response.
So,
here we have to rethink, I
think it's necessary, to
recover
the capacity for presence.
That we get out of frustration,
that we get out of this
closed world of the machine
and allow ourselves to return to contact,
return to what is
essential in human beings,
which has always been this,
being together, and together we learn.
Look,
if after everything I've told you
all this time, you
still think you need help,
go to a professional psychologist.
Our task today is monumental,
we have a lot of work.
From the pandemic until now,
people have discovered
that the life that  they were
distracted, busy,
covering up many things that they were suffering from. I
tell you this
because part of my work,
and with that I'll finish,
has consisted of investigating
what creates human suffering.
We live a part of our life
without knowing who we are,
we live a part of our life
that we don't like the way we are
and, when we begin to understand
what life is,
then we have a functional life, we have to get
married,
have children, we have to work, we have to
develop
intellectually, professionally...
Therefore, we achieve our great merit
in the part that is the functional part.
But, then, the critical stage arrives,
the stage where the unconscious,
the repressed,
our shadows, especially what I am,
but that I left aside,
everything that I am, but that I abandoned
to do something else, to
look good, to
please my family,
to be like everyone else...
What I left, what
I already had in me,
in middle age,
between 40 and  50,
knocks on the door
and demands its right to be.
And that
's when crises come to us. It
used to be called "the 40s crisis",
today we don't know where to put it, we do
n't know where to put it,
but a crisis comes to us that means
that everything I thought I was
turns out to be that I'm not comfortable being like that,
but, in addition, there are other aspects
that I would like to develop
that I haven't developed in myself.
And then I also
realize the disappointment
of having been a good boy or girl,
that I understood late and badly
that, by wanting everyone to love me,
the only thing I achieved
was for everyone to use me.
Therefore, when I reach this anxiety, when I
reach this crisis,
when this moment comes
when life asks me to be more myself,
then I have to let myself be helped.
There are people who solve this problem badly.
"I'm tired, I'm not interested in this,
now I'll be everything I've never been",
then
they  they become another figure,
but that is not the solution either
because, then, you do crazy things,
crazy things that are not necessary. It
all consists of being able to integrate
these two parts, this duality
that exists in us,
the part that we have developed
and the part that should not be
able to be integrated.
As Carl Jung said:
"Within a mandala,
which has a center in the heart
and that this heart makes everything integrate,
because everything that is rejected,
everything that is not integrated
will be repressed,
and what is repressed will be projected,
and from here the shadows appear".
Therefore, to do this exercise, it
is sometimes necessary to go
to health professionals,
in this case,
specifically, psychology. We will
help you in these aspects
that have to do with the crises
of our lives,
anxiety, depression,
difficulties at work, adapting,
problems with relationships...
Well, there are a series of problems
that are eternal
in the world of psychology,
that continue to be there
and we are here to facilitate.
But I discovered with my colleague
in the consultation,  Núria Molina,
I discovered that there was
another thing
that caused a lot of pain and suffering,
and that is that we count time.
Living by counting time is painful
because you see that time passes
and you still haven't resolved many things.
Time passes
and I'm still not who I thought I would be,
time passes and I still haven't achieved
that purpose I set for myself,
time passes and I'm still not rich,
time passes and I'm still not happy,
time passes
and I'm increasingly desperate
because I see that time passes.
So, whoever calculates
and whoever counts time
despairs.
Therefore, a great generator of anxiety
in people's lives is time.
Therefore, think, observe
how you treat time in your life.
Time is not the stopwatch, it
is not chronological time,
nor is it the linear time
that we live in the West,
we are born, we live and we die.
"Time is the nature
of what we were created from",
said the poet.
"Time", said Heidegger, philosopher,
"and being is the  "
What am I? Time of existence.
What am I? Time.
So, one thing is what I am, time,
the other is what I do
with this time that I am.
What do I do with my life? Do I
spend my day watching series?
Well, I spend it watching series,
but don't complain afterwards.
Then don't come and say:
"I wasted my time".
No, no, you haven't wasted your time.
How many people after a divorce,
a separation:
"I wasted my time, it has
swindled part of my life"?
No, no, you have dedicated
part of your life to this.
What you are you have dedicated to this. Is that it
? Have you seen that it is not?
Dedicate it to something else, perfect.
But what does "I have been swindled" mean?
What does "I wasted my time" mean?
No, no, you are always time,
you are in time always,
you are time.
So, decide
what to do with the time that you are.
Thank you very much, blessings to all.